<?xml version='1.0'?>
<!DOCTYPE refentry PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.2//EN"
 "http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.2/docbookx.dtd">
<refentry id="crimson.6">
<refentryinfo>
  <date>January 20 2007</date>
  <author>
    <firstname>Jens</firstname>
    <surname>Granseuer</surname>
    <address><email>jensgr@gmx.net</email></address>
  </author>
</refentryinfo>

<refmeta>
  <refentrytitle>crimson</refentrytitle>
  <manvolnum>6</manvolnum>
</refmeta>

<refnamediv>
  <refname>crimson</refname>
  <refpurpose>a hex-based tactical combat game</refpurpose>
</refnamediv>

<refsynopsisdiv>
  <cmdsynopsis>
    <command>crimson</command>
    <arg choice="opt">--level <replaceable>level</replaceable></arg>
    <arg choice="opt">--width <replaceable>w</replaceable></arg>
    <arg choice="opt">--height <replaceable>h</replaceable></arg>
    <arg choice="opt">--fullscreen 1|0</arg>
    <arg choice="opt">--sound 1|0</arg>
  </cmdsynopsis>

  <cmdsynopsis>
    <command>crimson</command>
    <group choice="req">
      <arg choice="plain">--help</arg>
      <arg choice="plain">--version</arg>
    </group>
  </cmdsynopsis>
</refsynopsisdiv>

<refsect1><title>Description</title>
  <para><application>Crimson Fields</application> is a tactical war
  game in the tradition of the popular
  <application>Battle Isle</application>. Two players
  command a number of units on a map of hexagons, trying to
  accomplish mission objectives ranging from defending important
  locations to simply destroying all enemy forces. Damaged units
  may be repaired or replaced by new recruits, while victorious
  squadrons will improve their abilities so they will be even
  more difficult to beat next time.</para>

  <para>The game can be played against a human adversary in
  hot-seat mode, over a network, or via e-mail, or against a computer
  player.</para>

  <para>The level editor
  <citerefentry><refentrytitle>cfed</refentrytitle><manvolnum>6</manvolnum></citerefentry>
  can be used to create your own levels.</para>
</refsect1>

<refsect1><title>Options</title>
  <para>If called without options <command>crimson</command> will
  open its main window using the settings from the last session or
  the defaults if no previous settings exist.</para>

  <variablelist>
    <varlistentry>
      <term><option>--level</option> <replaceable>level</replaceable></term>
      <listitem>
        <para>Skip the level selection window and load the mission
        file <replaceable>level</replaceable>. The file may be
        either a standard level file or a saved game. When starting a
        new game this way you will be playing a single map against the
        computer without any handicaps.</para>
      </listitem>
    </varlistentry>

    <varlistentry>
      <term><option>--width</option> <replaceable>w</replaceable></term>
      <listitem>
        <para>Set screen width to <replaceable>w</replaceable>.
        Minimum screen width is 320. Default is 800.</para>
      </listitem>
    </varlistentry>

    <varlistentry>
      <term><option>--height</option> <replaceable>h</replaceable></term>
      <listitem>
        <para>Set screen height to <replaceable>h</replaceable>.
        Minimum screen height is 240. Default is 600.</para>
      </listitem>
    </varlistentry>

    <varlistentry>
      <term><option>--fullscreen</option> 1|0</term>
      <listitem>
        <para>Turn fullscreen mode on/off. The default is to start
        in windowed mode.</para>
      </listitem>
    </varlistentry>

    <varlistentry>
      <term><option>--sound</option> 1|0</term>
      <listitem>
        <para>Turn sound on/off. The default is on.</para>
      </listitem>
    </varlistentry>

    <varlistentry>
      <term><option>--help</option></term>
      <listitem>
        <para>Print a usage message on standard output and exit.</para>
      </listitem>
    </varlistentry>

    <varlistentry>
      <term><option>--version</option></term>
      <listitem>
        <para>Print version information on standard output and
        exit.</para>
      </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
  </variablelist>

  <para>The display and sound options given to <command>crimson</command>
  on startup will be saved to file and restored on the next program
  start.</para>
</refsect1>

<refsect1><title>Getting Started</title>
<refsect2><title>Introduction</title>
  <para>The once peaceful planet Nexus has been invaded by beings calling
  themselves the Empire of Kand who are determined to conquer Nexus or
  destroy it completely. The public unrest has become violent as the
  people attempt revolution against the invasion, but the Empire of Kand
  are quick to silence opposition. Nexus is on the verge of war and its
  people have formed factions to battle the Empire. As a member of one
  of the major rebel factions, the Free Nexus Army, your goals are
  obvious: to drive the intruders back to whichever part of the galaxy
  they came from and restore peace on planet Nexus...</para>
  <para>(This is the background story for most of the included missions
  and the default campaign. There may be maps with entirely different
  settings.)</para>
</refsect2>
<refsect2><title>Main Menu</title>
  <para>The main screen presents a number of widgets to configure the
  game. The most important decision is whether you want to play a
  skirmish match, a campaign, or load a saved game. Skirmishes are
  stand-alone maps while campaigns consist of a number of maps which
  must be played (and won) in sequence. Each map that you advance to
  during a campaign will also be unlocked for skirmish matches. While
  campaigns can only be played against the computer, skirmishes can
  additionally be played as hot-seat matches (two players on one
  computer taking turns), e-mail matches (see <xref linkend="pbem"/>),
  or over a network, and when playing against the computer you
  get to choose which side you want to play on. For both game types
  you can optionally define a handicap, to make the game a bit easier
  or harder. What this means exactly depends on the map being played
  but in most cases a handicapped player will have fewer units or
  resources at his disposal than his opponent.</para>
  <para>The large box on the left lists all available skirmishes,
  campaigns, or saved games, while the box on the right displays a small
  image of the selected map or, for campaigns, the story. For
  skirmishes, the number in brackets shows the recommended number of
  players. Missions designed for one player are often rather unbalanced
  if played against another human since the computer plays so different
  from a human, although a handicap can sometimes fix this.</para>
  <para>After you have selected a map hit <guibutton>Start</guibutton>
  to enter the game.</para>
</refsect2>
<refsect2><title>First Steps</title>
  <para>After starting the match you will be presented with the mission
  briefing. Here you are given your orders and objectives to win the map.
  As both players usually have different and conflicting goals, each
  player gets his own briefing session at the beginning of his first
  turn.</para>
  <para>After the briefing you will be presented with the map. This
  is your command center. From here you can issue most of the orders
  that will determine the outcome of the mission. The first player
  commands the yellow units while the second player or computer
  takes control of the blue units.</para>
  <para>The map consists of small regions of land (or water) each known
  as a <emphasis>hex</emphasis> (sometimes also called
  <emphasis>field</emphasis> or <emphasis>square</emphasis>).
  Left-clicking on a hex selects that hex and moves the cursor to it. If
  there is a unit on the selected hex then a small bar will appear in
  the lower left of the screen showing the rank of the unit, its type,
  and the squad size (see <xref linkend="experience"/> for more
  information about ranks). If there is instead a building or shop on
  the selected hex, the information bar displays the name of the shop
  and possibly some icons representing special attributes (see
  <xref linkend="crystals"/> for details). Shops may occupy several
  fields, but they only have a single entrance, which is marked by the
  colour of the respective owner. Buildings with a white entrance are
  neutral and not controlled by any player.</para>
  <para>A right-click on one of your units generally brings up a context
  menu for that unit (this does not apply to enemy units). Here you can
  view the unit stats, or inspect its contents (transporters
  only). Other units like mine-sweepers may have special skills which
  also show up here. If the unit is not a transporter and does not offer
  any special skills, the menu is skipped and you are directly taken to
  the stats display.</para>
  <para>The stats window is basically divided in two parts. The top part
  shows the unit name and its values for speed, armour, and effectiveness
  against ground troops, aircraft, and ships in that order, from the top
  left to the bottom right. Most units have a weapon range of 1, meaning
  they can shoot at units one hex away (i.e. directly next to it). For
  units with different settings, the actual range is given in brackets
  after the weapon power. The second part of the window lists the most
  important terrain types. Shaded terrain indicates that the unit cannot
  cross that ground.</para>
  <para>Right-clicking anywhere but on a unit or pressing
  <keycap>F1</keycap> pops up the <guimenu>Game</guimenu> menu where you
  can review your mission objectives, take a look at an overview map, or
  save your game, for example.</para>
  <para>You select one of your units by simply clicking on it. Large parts
  of the map will now be shaded to indicate that the unit cannot move
  there. Unshaded enemy units are potential targets. To move to an
  accessible field or attack a foe, simply double-click the respective
  hex. If you accidentally sent your unit to a hex you did not want it to
  go to, right-clicking on the unit gives you the option of reverting the
  last move, as long as it did not trigger any special events.</para>
  <para>If you click twice on one of your shops or a neutral one, you
  enter that building. Of course, you can also move units into shops,
  although only some units (<emphasis>Infantry</emphasis> in the default set)
  can move into shops not owned by you, and some buildings may not allow
  all unit types. Quite often buildings are important mission objectives.
  Taking the enemy headquarters, e.g., is a very common goal. But even if
  you do not specifically need to control a certain shop for victory, it
  can still be very helpful as it may be possible to repair or build
  units (see <xref linkend="crystals"/>).</para>
  <para>When you have issued all orders, select <guibutton>End Turn</guibutton>
  from the <guimenu>Game</guimenu> menu. Your commands are then executed,
  fights are resolved, and your opponent gets his chance to strike
  back...</para>
</refsect2>
</refsect1>

<refsect1><title>Movement</title>
  <para>Each unit may only move once each turn, and only if it did not
  initiate combat on the same turn. <emphasis>Artillery</emphasis> and
  <emphasis>Anti-Aircraft Guns</emphasis> cannot attack if they have already
  been moved on the same turn. To move around on the map, a unit needs
  <firstterm>movement points</firstterm>. The number in the upper left
  corner of the unit information dialog (which can be brought up for one
  of your units by right-clicking it) indicates how many hexes the unit can
  move under optimal circumstances. The actual range is determined by
  several factors.</para>

  <para>For ordinary ground units the terrain can greatly reduce
  the range of action. The maximum can only ever be reached on
  roads, everything else will slow the unit down, and mountains
  more so than forest. For airborne units or ships, terrain is of
  no importance.</para>

  <para>Enemy units can be trapped in order to prevent them from
  using superior speed or to deny them access to certain areas of
  the map. A unit which attempts to cross a hex between two
  hostile units or one hostile unit and inaccessible terrain will
  be stopped immediately after passing through.</para>

  <para>A unit cannot leave a transport or building and enter
  another one on the same turn. Enemy buildings can only be
  conquered by infantry units.</para>
</refsect1>

<refsect1><title>Combat</title>
  <refsect2><title>Results</title>
    <para>Basically the probability to hit an enemy unit in combat
    is the same for all unit types, although the attacker always
    gets a slight advantage. This hit probability is then modified
    by effects such as experience, distance to the target, terrain,
    or wedging (see below). Similarly, each unit gets assigned a
    probability for evading an attack which is then modified by
    experience, terrain effects and blocking. If a unit scores a
    hit it will increase its attack pool by an amount equal to its
    strength. A unit which successfully evades an attack will have
    its defence pool grow by an amount equal to its defence or
    armour value. Finally, each attack pool is compared to the
    enemy's defence pool, and the resulting ratio determines the
    casualties on both sides.</para>
  </refsect2>

  <refsect2><title>Terrain</title>
    <para>Terrain is an important factor in combat as it can
    heavily influence a unit's effectiveness. For example, fighting
    on a road or open plains will greatly increase attacking
    strength but offers relatively poor defensive capabilities,
    whereas a unit in the mountains will profit from the higher
    position in both attack and defence. Terrain modifiers do not
    apply for aircraft.</para>
  </refsect2>

  <refsect2><title>Wedging</title>
    <para>Friendly units can help increase the combat strength of
    an attacking unit without attacking themselves. For each
    friendly unit which is adjacent to and capable of shooting at
    the defender, the attacker will get a 10 per cent bonus. If the
    unit is adjacent to the defender, but cannot attack it the
    bonus is reduced to 5 per cent. A friendly unit in the back of
    the defender will earn another 5 per cent bonus, or 10 if it
    could also attack. It does not matter whether a wedging unit
    actually attacks the defender. Wedging does not work for
    long-range attacks.</para>
  </refsect2>

  <refsect2><title>Blocking</title>
    <para>In a manner similar to wedging, defending units may
    improve their position in combat. For each friendly unit
    adjacent to the attacker and the defender, the defending unit
    will have its combat strength increased by 10 per cent. Just
    like wedging, blocking does not help against long-range
    attacks.</para>
  </refsect2>

  <refsect2 id="experience">
    <title>Experience</title>
    <para>Veteran units are usually much stronger than newly
    assembled ones. If you manage to wipe out an enemy unit your
    unit will receive three experience points. If the enemy is only
    damaged you will still get one point. Every three experience
    points a unit advances to a new rank which improves its combat
    skills. Still, a seasoned infantry unit will have a very hard
    time against a group of recently recruited heavy tanks.
    Destroying mines does not earn any experience points.</para>
  </refsect2>
</refsect1>

<refsect1 id="crystals"><title>Crystals</title>
  <para>Crystals represent the resources required to maintain and
  enlarge your army. You need them to repair damaged units or
  build new ones.</para>

  <refsect2><title>Repairs</title>
    <para>Units which have been damaged in combat can be repaired
    in any building equipped for this purpose (a
    <firstterm>workshop</firstterm>). To check whether a building
    is a workshop, click on it. For workshops a wrench icon will be
    displayed in the small info bar that appears in the lower left
    of the screen, and a repair button is available in the icon bar
    inside. Repairing will restore a unit to its full strength and
    requires an amount of 5 crystals, no matter what kind of unit
    it is or how badly is was damaged. Apart from the crystal cost
    the unit loses one experience point for each rookie that fills
    up an empty slot.</para>
    <para>The ability to repair damaged units is not necessarily
    limited to shops. Some unit types may offer the same service
    (from the standard unit set, for example, the
    <emphasis>Aircraft Carriers</emphasis> can bring aircraft back
    into shape). Repairs in units works exactly the same way as
    in workshops, and you also need to supply the crystals to do
    so.</para>
  </refsect2>

  <refsect2><title>Production</title>
    <para>To build new units you need some crystals and a
    <firstterm>factory</firstterm> (hammer icon). The amount of
    crystals required depends on the type of unit you want to
    build: A squad of light reconnaissance vehicles is cheaper
    than a group of heavy attack choppers. Most factories can not
    produce all unit types, even if you could afford it. If you
    click on the production button inside a factory, you are shown
    the list of units which can be built in this particular
    factory. Next to each unit type is the amount of crystals that
    will be consumed. Newly built units can only move on your next
    turn.</para>
  </refsect2>

  <refsect2><title>Mines</title>
    <para>To replenish your supply of crystals you need
    <firstterm>mines</firstterm>. Mines are buildings which
    'produce' a certain amount of crystals each turn.
    They can not be identified from the outside. Many maps do not
    have any mines at all, so it is always a good idea to consider
    carefully what you spend your resources on. Crystals can be
    transferred from one building to another (e.g. from a mine to
    a factory) using any transporter unit.</para>
  </refsect2>
</refsect1>

<refsect1 id="pbem"><title>Play-By-E-Mail</title>
  <para>If <application>Crimson Fields</application> is played in
  play-by-e-mail mode, the game will automatically be saved
  whenever a player ends her turn. The resulting save file can
  then be sent to your opponent using your favourite mail client
  program.</para>

  <para>On your first turn you will be asked for a password. You
  will be prompted for this password at the beginning of each of
  your turns to prevent your opponent from spying. Note, however,
  that the password only offers very mild protection if you are
  playing against deliberate cheaters. Choose your enemies
  carefully!</para>
</refsect1>

<refsect1><title>Files</title>
  <para>Unix
  <simplelist>
    <member><filename>~/.crimson/crimsonrc</filename></member>
    <member><filename>~/.crimson/levels/</filename></member>
  </simplelist></para>
</refsect1>

<refsect1><title>See Also</title>
  <para>
    <citerefentry><refentrytitle>cfed</refentrytitle><manvolnum>6</manvolnum></citerefentry>,
    <citerefentry><refentrytitle>bi2cf</refentrytitle><manvolnum>6</manvolnum></citerefentry>
  </para>
</refsect1>

<refsect1><title>Copyright</title>
  <para>Copyright &copy; 2000-2007 Jens Granseuer</para>
  <para>This software is distributed under the terms of the
  <ulink url="http://www.gnu.org/copyleft/gpl.html">GNU General Public
  License</ulink> (GPL).</para>
</refsect1>
</refentry>

